% Please edit documentation in R/utils.R
\name{txt_tagsequence}
\alias{txt_tagsequence}
\title{Identify a contiguous sequence of tags as 1 being entity}
\usage{
txt_tagsequence(x, entities)
}
\arguments{
\item{x}{a character vector of categories in the sequence of occurring (e.g. B-LOC, I-LOC, I-PER, B-PER, O, O, B-PER)}

\item{entities}{a list of groups, where each list element contains
\itemize{
 \item start: A length 1 character string with the start element identifying a sequence start. E.g. 'B-LOC'
 \item labels: A character vector containing all the elements which are considered being part of a same labelling sequence, including the starting element. 
 E.g. \code{c('B-LOC', 'I-LOC', 'E-LOC')}
}
The list name of the group defines the label that will be assigned to the entity. If \code{entities} is not provided each possible value of \code{x}
is considered an entity. See the examples.}
}
\value{
a list with elements \code{entity_id} and \code{entity} where 
\itemize{
 \item entity is a character vector of the same length as \code{x} containing entities, constructed by recoding \code{x} to the names of \code{names(entities})
 \item entity_id is an integer vector of the same length as \code{x} containing unique identifiers identfying the compound label sequence such that 
       e.g. the sequence 'B-LOC', 'I-LOC', 'I-LOC', 'E-LOC' (New York City District) would get the same \code{entity_id} identifier.
}
See the examples.
}
\description{
This function allows to identify contiguous sequences of text which have the same label or 
which follow the IOB scheme.\cr 
Named Entity Recognition or Chunking frequently follows the IOB tagging scheme 
where "B" means the token begins an entity, "I" means it is inside an entity,
"E" means it is the end of an entity and "O" means it is not part of an entity. 
An example of such an annotation would be 'New', 'York', 'City', 'District' which can be tagged as 
'B-LOC', 'I-LOC', 'I-LOC', 'E-LOC'.\cr
The function looks for such sequences which start with 'B-LOC' and combines all subsequent 
labels of the same tagging group into 1 category. This sequence of words also gets a unique identifier such 
that the terms 'New', 'York', 'City', 'District' would get the same sequence identifier.
}
\examples{
x <- data.frame(
  token = c("The", "chairman", "of", "the", "Nakitoma", "Corporation", 
           "Donald", "Duck", "went", "skiing", 
            "in", "the", "Niagara", "Falls"),
  upos = c("DET", "NOUN", "ADP", "DET", "PROPN", "PROPN", 
           "PROPN", "PROPN", "VERB", "VERB", 
           "ADP", "DET", "PROPN", "PROPN"),
  label = c("O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", 
            "O", "O", "B-LOCATION", "I-LOCATION"), stringsAsFactors = FALSE)
x[, c("sequence_id", "group")] <- txt_tagsequence(x$upos)
x

##
## Define entity groups following the IOB scheme
## and combine B-LOC I-LOC I-LOC sequences as 1 group (e.g. New York City) 
groups <- list(
 Location = list(start = "B-LOC", labels = c("B-LOC", "I-LOC", "E-LOC")),
 Organisation =  list(start = "B-ORG", labels = c("B-ORG", "I-ORG", "E-ORG")),
 Person = list(start = "B-PER", labels = c("B-PER", "I-PER", "E-PER")), 
 Misc = list(start = "B-MISC", labels = c("B-MISC", "I-MISC", "E-MISC")))
x[, c("entity_id", "entity")] <- txt_tagsequence(x$label, groups)
x
}
